<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of popery: or, A sermon preached at a visitation at Ashford in Kent vpon 2. Thess. 2.12. Wherein the marks of antichristianisme and signes of truth are opened and applied, and the question of the sauing and damning of thos. that follow Antichrist is explanted by the Scriptures. By Robert Abbott, preacher of the Word of God at Cranebrooke in Kent.</title>
            <author>Abbot, Robert, 1588?-1662?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 57</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115232</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 864:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of popery: or, A sermon preached at a visitation at Ashford in Kent vpon 2. Thess. 2.12. Wherein the marks of antichristianisme and signes of truth are opened and applied, and the question of the sauing and damning of thos. that follow Antichrist is explanted by the Scriptures. By Robert Abbott, preacher of the Word of God at Cranebrooke in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Abbot, Robert, 1588?-1662?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. L[egat] for Philemon Stephens, and Christopher Meredith and are to be sold at the Golden Lyon in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"Copies should have [3*]⁴, epistle to the preachers of the Deanery of Charing in Kent, but the British Library copy has it misbound after A8 of STC 59."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DANGER OF POPERY: <hi>OR,</hi> A SERMON PREACHED at a Viſitation at <hi>Aſhford</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> vpon 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein the marks of Antichriſtianiſme</hi> and ſignes of truth are opened and applied, and the Queſtion of the ſauing and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe that follow <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed by the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT ABBOTT, Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Cranebrooke</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>APOC. 14. 10.</bibl>
            <q>The ſame ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> and are to be ſold at the Golden Lyon in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15653:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15653:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND and Right VVorſhipfull Doctor KINGS LEY, <hi>Archdeacon of</hi> CANTERBVRY my louing friend; ROBERT ABBOTT wiſheth all increaſes of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in Gods Church heere, and glory hereafter through Ieſus CHRIST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull and Reuerend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat you thankfully and louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted when it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, commeth, you ſee, in another forme; crauing a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond veiw. Though what I intended could not all be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the allotted time, yet may it all be ſeene. If you thinke it may be vſefull in this ſecure age for any of the Cleargy vnder you, your countenancing of it may incourage others to reade it. I doubt nothing of your loue either to mee, or mine, much leſſe to the common good. This poore Sermon will (I hope) be found to ayme at good, becauſe at God, and againſt Antichriſt. It is
<pb facs="tcp:15653:3"/> true, it might haue beene the worke of farre more able, but not more willing. Therefore as ſuch a worke it is tendred vnto you, from him who deſires to continue to God a faithfull ſouldier againſt the Pope of Rome, and to your worſhip</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A poore friend and fellow-helper in the worke of Chriſt Ieſus, ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15653:3"/>
            <head>The danger of Popery, or a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached vpon 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 12.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>That all they might be damned, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued not the truth, but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Wiſe-man, who (as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith) hath his eyes in his head, may eaſily perceiue that in theſe words there is a fearefull danger, when they ſay (that all they might bee damned): and a full deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe which are in danger, when they ſay, they are ſuch who beleeue not the truth but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe. Concerning which it is impoſsible that either we ſhould be profitable learners or ſpeakers except we take a ſhort veiw of the whole chapter without which we cannot aptly vnderſtand this preſent text.</p>
            <p>In the chapter therefore you may conceiue<note place="margin">The chapter analyſed.</note> with mee two points: firſt, a doctrine; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly an vſe. The doctrine concernes <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt;</hi> and commeth in thus. There were ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers (as it ſeemes) in the Primitiue Church, who would haue perſwaded the Chriſtians that the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15653:4"/> day of iudgement was at hand. And hence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards grew that Atheiſticall queſtion in <hi>Peter,</hi> where is the promiſe of his comming? Now to<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 4.</note> preuent the danger of them, the Apoſtle giues an admonition, forced vpon their hearts with a graue and powerfull charge, that they would not<note place="margin">Verſe 1.</note> be troubled with ſuch a ſuggeſtion vpon what pretence ſoeuer. For what he ſaith, he giues a<note place="margin">Verſe 2.</note> double reaſon: the firſt drawne from the effect of that conceit; it would deceiue them: and the<note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> ſecond, from the proper reaſons of that effect; which are thoſe things which muſt happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts comming to iudgement; and theſe are two. The firſt is that Apoſtaſie or leauing<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 10. 20.</note> our ſtanding, and by faith we ſtand: and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle expounds it when he ſaith, that in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times ſome ſhall depart from the faith. The<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 1.</note> ſecond is the reuelation of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> and ſo comes in the doctrine concerning him. Which doctrine is firſt propounded, and ſecondly am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified. It is propounded both by ſetting downe what he ſhall be, and what he ſhall doe. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his eſtate naturall he ſhall be a Man: in reſpect of his eſtate ſinfull and curſed, he ſhall be a man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdition. Now, for what he ſhall doe both by oppoſition and ambition, the text ſaith, that he ſhall oppoſe and exalt himſelfe, as you may ſee.</p>
            <p>Secondly the Apoſtle doth amplifie this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,<note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> both by the corrupting cauſes of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> and by his furtherances and meanes of aduancement, as alſo by the perſons who ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15653:4"/> giue him intertainment. As for the corrupting cauſes they are three: firſt the perſons, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee ſhould haue binne knowne, that is, the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> who remembred not what <hi>Paul</hi> had taught them concerning him. Secondly the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note place="margin">Verſ. 5. Verſ. 6, 7. Aetas <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſti</hi> naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis ſub <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifacio</hi> 3. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultantis ſub <hi>Adriano</hi> 7. regnantis ſub <hi>Hildebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi> trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantis in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one 10. Crak.</hi> defenſ. con. <hi>Spal.</hi> cap. 4. pag. 21. v. 8. Verſ. 9. Verſ. 10.</note> which hindered his Reuelation, that is, hee which with-helde, to wit, the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperor, who did decline as the Roman Papacy crept vp. Thirdly, the perſon hindering his progreſſe that is, the Lord, <hi>who ſhall conſume him with the ſpirit of his mouth and aboliſh him with the brightnes of his comming.</hi> Now for the meanes of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> aduancement, the Apoſtle ſets them downe to bee theſe too (which wee find to bee true in our owne experience when wee looke vpon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Popery) to wit, ſignes and lying wonders in forged miracles, and deceaueablenes of vnrighteouſnes in guilded lies. Laſtly, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the perſons who ſhall giue <hi>Antichriſt</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment; they are deſcribed, by their condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are (ſaith the text) in a periſhing eſtate; by the cauſes of it, namely, their owne ſin (they receiued not the loue of the truth) &amp; gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (who therefore ſent them ſtrong deluſion); and laſtly, they are deſcibed by the Iſſue of all, that is, damnation, in this verſe which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded<note place="margin">Verſ. 1, 2.</note> vnto you. So that this followes vppon thoſe miſerable <hi>Antichriſtians,</hi> to be damned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is reuealed, God fights againſt him,<note place="margin">The Summe of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>
               </note> men willingly ſlight the truth, the Diuell fights for him, men beleeue lies and follow him, and God damnes them. This is the Summe.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15653:5"/>
            <p>Let not the following vſe bee hungred after till the proper place of it. For the preſent, thinke with your ſelues that euery man is apt to harken after others danger: and therefore if we heare<note place="margin">Tunc tua res agitur, &amp;,</note> of robbery or murther ye inquire who it was? Seing then that in theſe works ye hear of danger, of killing of bodies and ſoules, and robbing them of god and happineſſe, diligently attend to two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The perſons in danger, they who beleeue not the truth but haue pleaſure in vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</item>
               <item>2. The danger of the perſons, that all they might be damned.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The order of the Apoſtle is (I know) by this meanes inuerted, yet this I take to be the moſt proper &amp; naturall way of handling, firſt to know a thing before we know the adiunct of it, firſt to know a man before wee can know his danger.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the perſon if you aske me who are theſe miſerable <hi>Antichriſtians?</hi> I anſwere from<note place="margin">The perſons in danger.</note> the text.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> They are ſuch as beleeue not the truth but haue pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.</q>
            <p>They are deſcribed here by Infidelity in reſpect of the word of God; and by euil beleife in reſpect of the word of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Which deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that you may conceiue, conſider the foure tearms of it. Firſt, what is meant by the truth: ſecondly, what by not beleeuing the truth: thirdly, what is meant by vnrighteouſneſſe: fourthly, what by taking pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe. By truth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15653:5"/> you muſt vnderſtand the doctrine of the Goſpel contained in the Scriptures. Thus Chriſt expounds<note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 17.</note> it, ſanctifie them with thy truth, thy word is truth; which word is ſo called in three reſpects. Firſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the vndeceiueable nature of it. All other doctrines are either falſe, or may be vaine, or fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. They are falſe if they oppoſe the religion of the Scriptures. They may be vaine, whether they be naturall or ciuill, if they doe poſſeſſe vs, and captiuate or peruert our vnderſtanding: for theſe haue their places if they doe prepare vs for higher<note place="margin">Modò prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent ac non detineant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genium.</note> imployments, and doe not impriſon vs from God and his more ſauing truth. Secondly, the word is truth in reſpect of the imployment which God hath giuen it in the Church to be a rule and ſquare of all ſauing truth. As <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt build according to the patterne, ſo muſt we lay the ground of all ſauing<note place="margin">Heb. 8. 5.</note> and wholeſome truth according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Therefore when Chriſt meant to deſtroy by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and to deface the deformities of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> he giues <hi>Iohn,</hi> as a tipe of the Miniſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,<note place="margin">Apoc. 10. 8, 9.</note> the little booke to eate which is the word of God. Hee gaue him not the great Popiſh volumes of decretals, which, together with the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie in the Popes owne breaſts doe make vp the word of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> but the little volume of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture which maketh vp moſt fully the word of the Lambe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is called truth in regard of the worke of it: becauſe it doth confound errour and worke ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie in iudgement, heart, tongue, affections; and the whole conuerſation of thoſe, who without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15653:6"/> doe cleaue vnto it. For though ſome tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the iuſt iudgement of God, are giuen ouer to the blindneſſe of their minds, and rebellion of their wills, and ſo doe not ſubmit vnto the word, as thoſe who reſiſted the holy Ghoſt, yet ſo many as are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained<note place="margin">Acts. 7. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Acts. 28. 23. 24. Act. 2. 47.</note> vnto life and ſhall be ſaued, are by this meanes at ſome times or other reclaimed from their falſe courſes and added to the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thus you ſee what is meant by the truth; now if you aske mee what is meant by not beleeuing the truth? I anſwere, the not receiuing of it into our heads and hearts. For that which he called before<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſ. 2. 10.</note> the not receiuing the loue of the truth that they might be ſaued, heere he calleth, not beleeuing the truth. Beſides the power of beleeuing, is called a<note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 12.</note> receiuing by <hi>Iohn,</hi> when he ſaith, that as many as receiued him to them he gaue a right to be the ſons of God, euen to them that beleeue in his name. The contrary to this not beleeuing is expreſſed by three ſignificant phraſes, namely, <hi>ſealing, grafting, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Eſay</hi> ſaith; <hi>Seale vp the Law among my Diſciples.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 8. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fowles pecke the wheate in the ſtony ground, but that which is ſealed vp is not eaſily come by to be ſtolne away. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, receiue with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note place="margin">Iam 1. 21.</note> the word which is graffed in you. As the graft is receiued of the ſtocke into one body; ſo the word muſt bee incorporated into vs; and not to bee ſeparated from vs but to our ruine. The Pſalmiſt<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 11.</note> ſaith that I haue hid thy promiſe in my heart, that I might not ſinne againſt thee. As bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> kept<note place="margin">Luk. 2. 19. 51.</note> the ſayings of Ieſus Chriſt in her heart: ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> kept the promiſes of God by faith. When the truth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15653:6"/> is not thus ſealed vp and hid in our hearts by being taken into our nature, that we may liue and die with it, but the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pit is ſuffered<note place="margin">Apo. 9 2.</note> to darken our ſoules? then are wee ſaid not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But what now is meant by vnrighteouſneſſe in this place? Nothing but falſhood. For as ſinne in generall is taken for falſe doctrine, as when Chriſt<note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 46.</note> ſaith, which of you can rebuke mee of ſinne? as we ſee by the oppoſition there, but if I ſay the truth why doe ye not beleeue mee? ſo vnrighteouſneſſe in particular in this place, as we ſee by the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here, not beleeuing the truth, but hauing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in vnrighteouſneſſe. And falſhood may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnrighteouſnes, both becauſe it carryeth vs from the rule of righteouſneſſe which ſhould informe our<note place="margin">Quod efficit tale illud ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt magis tale</note> vnderſtanding and reforme our hearts and whole conuerſation that we might haue an accepted righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: as alſo becauſe it is a fearefull cauſe of vnrighteouſneſſe. The Romanes abuſing the law of Nature, and turning the truth of God into a lye,<note place="margin">Ro. 1. 24, 25.</note> were giuen vp in their hearts, vnto luſts, vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and other Gentiles as well as they, hauing their cogitations darkened, and hearts hardened for<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 18, 19</note> want of ſauing truth, gaue themſelues vnto wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to worke all vncleanneſſe with greedineſſe.</p>
            <p>Thus you vnderſtand vnrighteouſneſſe, one thing more will cleere all, and that is, what may be meant by taking pleaſure in it?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I anſwere, the giuing of our hearts to the pleaſing enticements of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> as effeminate perſons giue themſelues to the pleaſing enticements of harlots.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15653:7"/> For there are three ſorts of the followers of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:</hi> Some that are ſimply ſeduced, ſuch are they who are ſaid to dwell on the earth, that is, in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſtate and condition of the Church, who were<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. 14.</note> deceiued by the ſignes and great wonders of the beaſt. Some that are by feare and torture compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſuch are thoſe ſmall and great, rich and poore,<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. 16, 17.</note> bond and free, whom he made to receiue his marke, or elſe they ſhould neither buy nor ſell. Some alſo there are that are carnally minded, who liue in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with the whoore of Babel; ſuch as are ſaid to commit fornication with her, and to be drunke with<note place="margin">Apoc. 17. 2.</note> the wine of her fornications, and to waxe rich with the aboundance of her pleaſures. Of theſe doth the<note place="margin">Apoc 18. 3.</note> holy Apoſtle ſpeake in this place.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I (as God hath inabled mee) opened vnto you the words of the Apoſtle; by which you may perceiue that the text driues at the deſcription<note place="margin">Who are <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtians.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Antichriſtians,</hi> and telleth vs that they are ſuch as receiue not with high eſtimation and reuerence the word of the Lambe but make a religion and take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the word of the beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Now of this deſcription we may make a double vſe. Firſt for inſtruction, and ſecondly, for exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Firſt, it teacheth vs that they are moſt proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Antichriſtians, who take delight in the whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and idolatrie of the Church of Rome, and of this they carry a double brande.</p>
            <p>Firſt, their ſlighting of the word of God in the Scriptures (as moſt of vs know). For as the Pope doth vnyoke himſelfe from it by the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, as he is that <hi>Caiphas;</hi> by the ſpirit of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15653:7"/> as he is the Church; by the ſpirit of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibilitie as he is Chriſts Vicar; by pretended tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as hee is the Churches Treaſurer; and by<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. Theſſ. 2. 8.</note> the power of diſpenſation as he is that lawleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: ſo his followers from him doe diſgrace and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance the Scriptures that they may walke in darkneſſe without controule: Are we not daily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted<note place="margin">Pſeudo-ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu: a late Popiſh booke ſo called.</note> with their pleading againſt the Scriptures, &amp; with their deriding of vs for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant appeales vnto it? Hence is it that they fill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with much durt to caſt in our faces for the Scriptures ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, they tel vs that all heretikes run vnto the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. As the Scribes and Phariſes &amp; other Iewes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt: So <hi>Ebion, Corinthus, Menander, Arius</hi> &amp; heretikes of all times. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Why here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes appeale to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> We anſwer, that it is true that heretikes do take this courſe &amp; that for three cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, becauſe their conſciences haue tolde them that there hath beene ſome diuine thing in them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all writings whatſoeuer: and therefore they thought that if they could ſhelter their conceits vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wings of the Scripture they were ſafe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, becauſe they ſee that all the members of the Church, whom the deuill doth ſeeke princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to annoy, doe loue and make them their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, comforter, and counſeller; which they will<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> more willingly heare then all the world. Heretickes therefore being willing to propagate their errours will corrupt ſuch friends as are moſt deare to the parties whom they would haue to imbrace them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe they haue beene thus farre ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the doctrine of the Church, that they know it maketh the Scriptures a ſpirituall iudge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15653:8"/> vnder God as from liuing oracles, what is neceſſary to be held and practiſed in all fundamentall matters of faith and obedience. For theſe reaſons (I ſay) haue heretickes runne vnto the Scriptures: yet for all that as Chriſt obiected Scripture in truth againſt the Scribes, Phariſes, and deuill who obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it againſt him in hypocriſie: euen ſo muſt we.</p>
            <p>What though mine enemie ſay that he hath part in mine inheritance, and that this and this peece of land is his, ſhall I therefore begger my ſelfe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne it ouer vnto his ſpoile? ſhall I not rather ſearch out my euidences and cleere the truth of my right and the falſhood of his claime by thoſe meanes which the kingdome where I dwell will afford? what though a Baſtard ſay that he hath right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to my land: ſhall I therefore renounce all my owne birth-right?</p>
            <p>So though all the enemies of faith and baſtards in the Church, ſhall claime a right in our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and portion of the Scriptures ſhall we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forſake all our liuelyhood &amp; comfort in them? ſhall wee not rather labour by the benefit of thoſe gifts which God hath giuen, (not to the Pope and his adherents) but to the true Church of God, to wit, the gift of interpretation, tongues, wiſedome, knowledge, prayer, and the like, to cleere the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of falſhood and the glory of truth?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Yea but meane while (you will ſay) that the fancies and errors of wicked perſons are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently condemned in the Scriptures. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Bee not too raſh. Is not diueliſh temptation ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the Scriptures becauſe the Diuell doth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15653:8"/> tempt Chriſt from the Scriptures abuſed? vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt or vncharitable Suites are ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by Law though wrangling perſons will ſtill pretend law to maintain them: ſo are all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies ſufficiently conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned in Scriptures though Heretickes ſeeke to maintaine them by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures abuſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> You will ſay, how then is it that they are not conuinced by them? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere two things: firſt, the Scripture is ſufficient to conuince, (without which it cannot make perfect) elſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> would<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 17. Math. 12. 3. Math. 22. Math<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> not haue vſed it to that end; neither would the Phariſies nor Sadduces, nor the Diuel be put to ſilence by that meanes. Secondly, many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands haue binne conuinced by it to the rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their iudgments. And if ſome are obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſhall wee ſay that it is not in the Scriptures power to conuince? Noe; rather tis Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice<note place="margin">Act. 7. 51.</note> to puniſh their obſtinacy and to giue them ouer to periſhing as thoſe that reſiſt the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> You will ſay how can the Scripture conuince them when it is not their Iudge? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I anſweare: It is their Law to rule &amp; guide their actions; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is their Iudge: for Iudges are but miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the law.</p>
            <p>It is the law which doth iudge of claymes, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, inheritances, treſpaſſes, and the like; and the Iudges doe not make the iudgement of the Law but pronounce it: And ſo the Miniſtery of Gods Church and people doth but pronounce the iudgment of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>And if ſometimes it doth pronounce amiſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15653:9"/> (as it may do though it take neuer ſo good heed to the word of God, in thoſe things which are not neceſſarily beleiued vnto ſaluation) it is not becauſe the ſcripture doth not exactly iudge, but becauſe wee know in part and are not perfectly<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13, 12.</note> inlightned, and ſo may miſſe of the right mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſome things; as the beſt Iudges in ſome caſes may miſſe the right meaning of the law.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thus haue I ſhewed you in ſome few particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars<note place="margin">Papiſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue lies.</note> how the Papiſts ſleight the truth (and yet in vaine) to pull vpon themſelues the firſt badge of <hi>Antichriſtians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is their delighting in that Lie of <hi>Antichrist</hi> which is heere called Vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is that great Theife who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> not in by the doore into the folde: looke therefore as a theife puts out the candle that ſo beeing deceiued he may deceiue others; ſo doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> put out the light of the ſcriptures (ſo much as he can) that his wretched lies &amp; ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may the more eaſily be ſettled vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his followers. All falſe religions are lies, but there is no religion in the world (that I know) which makes lying a part of their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae fraudes: pia mendacia</note> but that of <hi>Rome.</hi> They haue their Aequiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, their godly deceites and lyes; ſuch as are made and told for the aduancement of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſtirre vp deuotion. Hence doe they belie their aduerſaries both in their liues, doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, &amp; deaths; as we know in <hi>Luther, Caluine, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rob. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> cen. quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undam ſcript. et mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti abi.</note> 
               <hi>biſhop King,</hi> &amp; others. Hence do they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit falſe Fathers, and purge the true ones to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15653:9"/> make them ſpeake as they pleaſe. Hence do they thruſt thouſand of lies vpon the poore people, as the hiſtorie of <hi>Loreto,</hi> where we read of Pope <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulius,</hi> hauing performed his deuotion in our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes<note place="margin">Hiſt. of Lor lib. 2. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2</note> Chappels, by hir protection was preſerued from a Cannon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhot which beat down his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory where he was &amp; yet hurt not his Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: and of the <hi>Dalmatian</hi> Prieſt (that man of<note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note> true ſimplicity and great deuotion) who hauing his bowels plucked out of his body by the cruel Turkes, becauſe he would not abiure Chriſt, tooke his guts in his hand (if any will beleeue it) and ſo went a iourney of many dayes to <hi>Loreto,</hi> and there was cured. They haue alſo their Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends both in Latine &amp; Engliſh, and other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, which haue binne and are of dayly vſe to abuſe the credulous people. There we reade of the power of S. <hi>Patricks</hi> Prayer, which made a ſheepe bleate in the mans belly that had ſtole it. There wee read of the noble knight who<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>genda au de S. Patr. pa.</hi> 37 Vbi ſupra de Annunciat. pag. 38. See Beards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tract. from the Rom. Rel. D. Featly hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> append. to Fiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> net pag. 30. 31 32. An old poſt. Manuſcrip.</note> could learn no other leſſon than theſe two words <hi>Aue Maria;</hi> but to make amends, hee did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them with ſo great deuotion that when hee was dead and buried, a Lilly ſprung out of his tounge, euery leaf whereof had <hi>Aue Maria</hi> ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon it with golden letters, to the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the beholders. I might tell you of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heretick who was conuerted to the faith by ſeeing S. <hi>Anthonies</hi> Horſe worſhip the Hoſte, that is, the bread in the Sacrament: and of S. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> his Lambe which vſed to goe to the Maſſe &amp; kneele downe to the eleuation: and of a little
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15653:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15653:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15653:11"/> child that did ſtart out of the Sacrament when one did cut it, of an euill minde; which after a goodly proceſſion entered into the forme againe and ſo was deuoutly receiued of the paenitent of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender. I could fill you with ſuch Romiſh lies to make you loath againe: all which the poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being ſeduced, do ſuck in vnder the pretence of the ſpirit of infallibillity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tells<note place="margin">Ample de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. of Chriſt, doct chap, 6. p. 124.</note> vs that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the holy Church and the Spouſe of God, and hath the holy Ghoſt for her Maſter; and therefore there is no danger that ſhee ſhould be deceiued, or that ſhee ſhould doe or teach others to doe any thing that were againſt the Commandements of God. Vnder this pretence, what ſuperſtitious ſeducements<note place="margin">Tria igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipia: In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Philoſophos, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra neg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia: inter me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicos, vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus ſpecifica: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theologos eccleſia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Walt. Rayl. Preface.</note> ſhall not be ſwallowed downe without examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? If, as the Philoſopher cryeth out to thoſe that would diſpute, it is a Principle: ſo if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt can but alledge his Catholike Church, it is ſufficient to dampe all doubts, and to worke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to all lyes, be they neuer ſo palpable and notorious.</p>
            <p>Let them goe (my brethren) with theſe two badges of Antichriſtians, to wit, their ſleighting <hi>the Truth of the Lambe,</hi> and their <hi>beleeuing the word of the Beaſt:</hi> Let vs pittie and pray for them, that ſo many as are of the number of his ſealed ones, might be pulled out of theſe miſerable ſnares, and goe out of Babylon, <hi>that they be not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 4.</note> 
               <hi>partaker of her ſinnes, and ſo of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> But as for vs, let vs (in the ſecond place) be exhorted to entertaine and embrace the Truth,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15653:11"/> that wee may prooue our ſelues not to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians. It is the Truth alone, in which the ſufficiencie of our Soules is communicated vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The ancient Chriſtians perceiuing that world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men did place their ſufficiencie in their wealth (to ſignifie, that that ſufficiencie which commeth to vs by our riches, commeth not from them, but through Chriſt) ſtamped vpon their Coyne a Cloud with this voice or Motto, <hi>This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne in whom I am highly delighted:</hi> So wee may ſtampe Chriſt vpon Truth, as being that wherein wee haue fellowſhip with him who is our plentifull redemption, and the ſufficiencie of our bodies and ſoules by Truth.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, how may we be aſſured that<note place="margin">Queſt. How wee may know our religion to be the truth.</note> our religion is the truth, that ſo we may receiue it to the comfort of our ſoules? I anſwer; there are three things which may ſettle a quiet and humble ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, The foundation and ground-worke of our religion is that doctrine wholly and entirely which was preached by the Apoſtles, as ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to conuert men to the faith and to make them fit to receiue the Sacrament of Baptiſme. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare<note place="margin">Act. 2. Act. 3. Acts 7. Acts 10. Act. 13 &amp;c.</note> the Articles of our religion with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Apologies of <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of Gods ſeruants. If it be ſo that their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was ſufficient to conuert Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles and to bring them into couenant with God; and our doctrine be wholly &amp; entirely one with theirs, why ſhould any that haue not the ſpirit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15653:12"/> of contention and contradiction doubt that our religion is not the truth?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, our religion agreeth with the very nature of true religion which muſt be, an holy art of liuing well. There is no article of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Pet, Geiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus in actis Synod. Dor. pag. 282.</note> which driues not at this. Though that foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh hereticke in the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> could not ſee how the doctrine of three in one could further godlineſſe, yet Chriſt teacheth that euen that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract article doth it: for when he prayeth to his Father, that as <hi>Hee and his Father are one,</hi> ſo they<note place="margin">Ioh, 17. 21, 22, 23.</note> may be <hi>one in them,</hi> doth he not teach, that the Vnitie in Trinitie doth further our vnitie in our ſelues and the myſticall body? Now if true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be tryed by this generall nature of it wee ſhall finde two things. Firſt, that Popery (which is a religion whereby Chriſt is profeſſed to bee the Lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world, and men are baptized into the name of Chriſt, but he is applyed by the falſe meanes of merit, penall ſatisfactions, maſſes and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, and we are made one in his body by a falſe and vſurping Prince in ſtead of Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Eph. 4 11, 12.</note> Prophets, Euangeliſts, Paſtours, and Teachers) this Popery, I ſay, is not the art of liuing well. For firſt it hides the rule of liuing well, that is, the certaine will of God in the Scriptures by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouding them with vncertaine tradition. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it carrieth vs away from God to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as Hee-ſaints, Shee-ſaints, Maskes, Images, thorough which it is great difficultie to peirce to God by their muddy diſtinctions. Thirdly, it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15653:12"/> keepes their followers blinde ſo as they know not what they doe in their Latine ſeruice: and<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 1. de Iuſtif. cap. 7. fides meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us per igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quam per notitiam definitur. Eph. 4. 18.</note> their faith is better defined by ignorance then knowledge. Fourthly, it giues libertie to many ſinnes, as ignorance whereby they are made ſtrangers from the life of God, Inceſt, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, periury, rebellion and what not, ſeeing they haue thoſe who are ſubiect to the like paſſions, who, as Iudges, of ſinnes committed after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,<note place="margin">Bellar. ample declar. cap. de paen. pag. 210</note> can appoint penances ſatisfactory to God and pronounce abſolute abſolutions. Secondly, though Popery be not an Art of liuing well, yet our religion (whereby Chriſt is honoured by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in him alone for ſaluation, &amp; flying to theſe meanes of application which he hath appointed as the word, faith, Sacraments of Chriſt (who alone hath power to ſet ſeales to the couenant of grace, and prayer) this religion (I ſay) wholly aymes at good life. As the truth doth ſo it aymes<note place="margin">Ioh, 17. 17.</note> at the ſanctification of the heart: not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the outward acts of ſin by the contrary exerciſes of godlineſſe and righteouſneſſe, as the act of whooredome by continency, the act of drunkenneſſe by ſobrietie, the acts of all ſinnes by watchfulneſſe, faſting, and prayer and the like: and not onely ſtrugling at the corruptions of the inferiour faculties and brutiſh powers of the ſoule: but oppoſing the very enmity of the minde, ignorance of the vnderſtanding, darkneſſe and varietie of thoughts, ſtupiditie and fury of conſcience, rebellion of willes, and if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other diſorderlineſſe (as there is too much)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15653:13"/> either in ſoule or body, that doth exalt it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his moſt holy and righteous law.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Yea, but doe they not cry out that our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on giues liberty to ſinne by our doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Free-will, Iuſtification, Merits, aſſurance of ſaluation, perſeuerance of the Saints, and the like? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> It is true, they doe ſo; but it is from falſe grounds. For though we ſay that by nature, we haue no free-will to good, yet it is by our owne default, and therefore we haue iuſt cauſe to be humbled for it: and we are bound (for reformation) to giue attendance to the word, and to waite (as the poore <hi>Lazars</hi> at the poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi> for the deſcending of the Angell) that wee ouer-ſlip not the acceptable time and the houre of ſaluation. And this wee are able to doe, being a matter of outward diſcipline, and yet wee doe not. When the Bleſſing is giuen, wee are with <hi>Eſau</hi> hunting; in which reſpect wee may be iuſtly left in our ſinne. Againe, though wee ſay that wee are not iuſtified by our workes, yet they are the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fruits of our ſanctification, and the neceſſarie way to ſaluation, without which no man <hi>ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> And though we abhorre the thoughts<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> of Merits in the notion of the Church of Rome, yet wee ſay that wee cannot comfort our hearts without the preſence of <hi>Good workes,</hi> for other neceſſarie vſes. And how can the doctrine of<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 14.</note> aſſurance of ſaluation, and perſeuerance, lead to ſinne, when wee cannot be aſſured but by holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor perſeuere but in the vſe of the holy meanes of ſaluation?</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15653:13"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, as our Religion is a Doctrine of Veritie and Pietie, ſo it giues moſt ſound peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the houre of death and day of affliction. There is little or no certaintie or aſſurance in the principall acts of the Popiſh Religion, as I ſhall ſhew in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>As firſt, in reſting vpon the Traditions of the Church. Wee are ſure that the Scripture is the Word of God: wee haue the teſtimonie of men, but the teſtimonie of God is greater; for it is embraced by enemies as well as by friends, and is confirmed by the Miracles of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles: but wee cannot be ſo aſſured of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in drie Communions. Wee are ſure that Chriſt ordained two diſtinct ſignes, and that God is pleaſed when wee doe what hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: but wee cannot be aſſured, that God is pleaſed with halfe Communions (that is, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh receiuing of the Bread without the Wine) vnder pretence of Concomitancie; no, though wee were ſure that Chriſt were corporally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: becauſe the Lords Supper is a ſeale and ſigne of our crucified Lord, when his bodie and bloud were ſeuered; as he ſaith, <hi>This is my bodie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>which is giuen for you,</hi> and, <hi>This is my bloud which is ſhed for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in the Popes Monarchicall headſhip. Wee are ſure that Chriſt is the head of the Church; becauſe it is his office, and hee is of infinite power &amp; influence, yea and preſent with<note place="margin">Secundum eſſe perſonale</note> vs by his diuine power and vertue. But we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15653:14"/> be aſſured that the Pope is the head of the Church; no not in reſpect of outward admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 11. 12.</note> and gouernment: becauſe God hath not ſanctified one man onely, but many for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of the Saints, and edification of the body of Chriſt. Though in reſpect of Chriſt the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church is Monarchicall, yet in reſpect of Chriſts Biſhops and Miniſters it is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocraticall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, in prayer in a tongue not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the people. Wee are ſure that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to pray in our mother tongue (for euery<note place="margin">Pſaſ. 250.</note> tongue ſhall praiſe the Lord) yea and the Papiſts will confeſſe it; for euen they haue ſome pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in vulgar tongues, as their Manuel of godly prayers, <hi>Ieſus Pſalter</hi> and the like. But wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be aſſured of Gods accepting ſeruice in an vnknowne tongue: becauſe though God vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, yet the people cannot with vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 16. They may giue a fainte, lazy, haſty, and ignorant Amen. but not ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. Godw. Moſ. &amp; Aar. pag 90, 91. Ex. 20. 5. Leuit. 26. 1. Deut. 4. 15, 19. &amp; 5, 8. Eſ. 40.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, In adoration of Images. We are ſure that we may worſhip God without them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence; becauſe God hath neuer comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or required ſuch pretended helpes, yea and the Papiſts doe ſometimes pray without them, as in ſome of their priuate Oriſons, and in the time of Lent, when they are couered: But wee cannot be ſure that ſuch worſhip can pleaſe God, becauſe the Scripture is ſo punctuall againſt them, and they are ſuch ſnares to tye our deuotions below.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, in inuocation of Saints. Wee are ſure
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15653:14"/> that we may call vpon God, becauſe he hath bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> vs, and hath promiſed to heare and to helpe vs; yea, and the Papiſts themſelues hold this lawfull: But wee cannot be aſſured, that calling vpon the Saints pleaſeth eyther God, or them, or that they doe heare, or can helpe. The like wee may ſay of the Adoration of the Hoſte, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially becauſe we know not the Prieſts intention; and of many other Articles of their Trent Faith: whereof if wee cannot be aſſured, how can they giue vs comfort either in life or death?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee (in ſome meaſure) how you may be aſſured that our religion is the truth. If now you will aske me, how then it could poſſible bee that the world could ſo much be deceaued by Rome. I anſwere: becauſe the ſmoake of the bottomles<note place="margin">Apoc. 9. 2.</note> pit had darkned the Sun and ayre, and the Lambs hornes were vpon the head of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. 11.</note> foule beaſt. Looke therefore as if a Traytor car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the colours of a Prince in warre, all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſouldiers doe flock vnto him, guard him, &amp; fight vnder his Banner, till the Traitor be knowne and the Treaſon be diſcouered: So the Popes of Rome retaining the common principles of faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Communia fidei princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia. Cypr.</note> and manners, and profeſſing themſelues to bee Colour-bearers to Ieſus Chriſt, without which they could not ſo eaſily haue inſinuated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the hearts of the World (their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion giuing good occaſion of enquiring after them, and cleauing to them); moſt of the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne<note place="margin">Profeſſio opportunum fuit inquiren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di exordium.</note> Chriſtians, whom hee had wrought by power and policie, flocked vnto him: but when
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15653:15"/> his pretences were diſcouered, and they would no longer take his part againſt Chriſt, then hee makes a faction and head againſt vs in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, and excommunicateth vs (like the Iewes that caſt out their brethren and ſaid, <hi>Let the Lord be glorified</hi>) as if it were our fault that<note place="margin">Eſa. 66. 5. Columba Noae, pag 28, 29, 30.</note> we would not drinke his poyſon, and not his, who was ſo vncharitable and trecherous, as to offer it vnto vs who did flye vnto him for ſhelter. Yet let not this his furious and Antichriſtian courſe diſmay vs, but let vs in deſpight of all his power and policie, beleeue the truth of the Lambe, and ſtoppe our eares againſt the vnrighteouſneſſe of the Beaſt; or elſe let vs hearken to what doth follow to be handled, <hi>That they might all be damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Heere is the danger of theſe <hi>Antichriſtians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The danger of Antichriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</note> Such as haue poyſoned heads reiecting the word of truth, and poyſoned harts taking pleaſure in falſhood, which is manifeſted two wayes: firſt by an eager purſuite of the thinges of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> without examination; as if they ſhould ſay, we will be thus; becauſe we will be thus, doating vpon a ſpirit of infallibilitie: ſecondly, by a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell quelling, killing, and ſacrificing the oppoſers with fire and ſword, (ſuperſtition being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally cruell) of ſuch (I ſay) that the Apoſtle ſaith</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> They ſhall be damned.</q>
            <p>But you will ſay that the text ſaith they ſhall onely bee iudged. The Popiſh <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emists</hi> ſay ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede: They would haue the puniſhment of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15653:15"/> the followers of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> be as ſmal as they can;<note place="margin">Whether Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be iudged.</note> &amp; I cannot blame them: for it is naturall to euery creature to ſeek to preſerue it ſelfe; but it will not ſerue their turne heere: for firſt, the greatneſſe of the ſin, which is the contempt of the Goſpel, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for infinite more than iudging. For if the word ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt, and euery<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 2. 3.</note> tranſgreſſion and diſobedience receiued a iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of reward, how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſaluation? Secondly, the greatnes of the iudgement going before ſhewes that this can be no leſſe then damnation: for what elſe can<note place="margin">2 Theſſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> follow ſtrong deluſions which infatuate a man, &amp; are ſent in wrath? Thirdly, as the word it ſelf doth ſignifie to iudge, ſo to puniſh &amp; condemne. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, what haue I to doe to iudge them that are without. i. puniſh by exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 12.</note> Againe, whooremongers &amp; adulterers God will iudg, that is puniſh. So <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, though he<note place="margin">Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.</note> iudge them not who contemne his Goſpell, yet his word ſhall iudge, that is, condemne them.<note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 47. 48.</note> 
               <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaith to the Iewes, iudge him according to your owne law, that is, condemne him. So<note place="margin">In the new tranſlation.</note> alſo in many other places as well as in this text, &amp; that according to the iudgment of our Engliſh Church which is not to bee ſlighted.</p>
            <p>From hence then (for the clearing of the text)<note place="margin">Whether all Papiſts ſhall be damned.</note> will ariſe this dueſtion; <hi>whether all Papiſts ſhal be damned?</hi> I anſwere; God forbid we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to imbrue our heads or hands in the blood<note place="margin">In my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon called the tryall of true religion</note> of any. The cruelty of their falſe religion &amp; the mercy of ours is well enough known, as I haue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15653:16"/> ſhewed elſe-where. Therefore we ſay three things.<note place="margin">In my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon called the tryall of true religion.</note> Firſt that there are common principles in the Church of Rome, which being known, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with harts willing to be informed in the truth, purpoſes and indeauours to know and doe a right &amp; holy obedience to what is knowne by thoſe principles ſo far as they are come, may bring men to ſaluation. For who doubts but that the Beleife, the ten Commaundements, the Lords Prayer, and the Sacraments doe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all ſauing fundamentall points of Faith and practice? Theſe therefore being in the Church of Rome (though with much corruption) vpon the former limitations may affoard grounds of ſaluation to them to whom God giues power with an honeſt hart to receiue them. Secondly we ſay that in the midſt of Popery God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued a remnant according to the election of grace, which is called the Temple of God, and Gods people, who by theſe meanes, haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained<note place="margin">2. Theſſ 2. 4. Apoc. 18. 4.</note> to ſaluation. Thirdly, we ſay, that ſuch haue not bin members of the Popiſh Apoſtacy (wherein euery liuing thing died) though in the Romane Church: for hauing knowledge of the<note place="margin">Apoc. 16. 3.</note> common principles and being ignorant, or at the leaſt not ſo fully ſtated in the pernicious errours of the Popiſh corruptions, though they haue bin in that Church, yet they haue not beene of it, as many of our forefathers from age to age.</p>
            <p>When therefore the holy Ghoſt ſaith, that they ſhall be damned, we muſt (by the helpe of the ſame holy Ghoſt in his word) diſtinguiſh of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15653:16"/> 
               <hi>Perſons, of doctrines, and of times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As for Perſons in the Church of Rome, they are of two ſorts. Firſt, ſuch as haue the name of<note place="margin">1 Perſons.</note> the beaſt and the number of his name, that is, ſuch as are in outward communion with him,<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. 17.</note> who though they are deceiued, yet they may haue docible hearts and mindes willing to learne when our prouident God doth offer opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Secondly, ſuch as worſhip the Beaſt and his Image and receiue his markes, that is, ſuch as are in inward fellowſhip and myſterie with him,<note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 9, 10.</note> being by wilfulneſſe and reſolution, as it were, imbowelled in that ſtate: of theſe the holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>that they ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, touching doctrine, they are of three ſorts, ſome are the foundation; and this is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctrines,</hi> Fundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Veritatis 2. Salutis. 1. Cor. 3. 12.</note> either the foundation of truth, ſuch are all doctrines which haue ground in the word of God; ignorance of much of which may ſtand with ſaluation, ſo that it bee not affected: and they who know moſt doe not know all: or elſe the foundation of ſaluation, ſuch are all doctrines which doe concerne the cauſes of our ſaluation, and the neceſſary meanes of application. It is the ignorance of theſe which doth breede periſhing.</p>
            <p>Other doctrines againe are vpon the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of building on the foundation, <hi>gold, ſiluer, precious ſtones, timber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>hay, or ſtubble,</hi> that is, varietie of doctrine which hath beene or is of worth and vſe, as theſe things whereto it is compared. And of this as there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15653:17"/> hath beene much (as gold and ſiluer) in euery age of the Church, ſo there hath beene much (as hay and ſtubble), by ſophiſticall ſpeculations, forged traditions, humane inuentions, and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous and fryarly interpretations of the holy Scriptures. Such traſh is to be ſwept away as dung out of the ſtreetes, that it might not defile our Pulpits, but that the glory of the word of God might appeare (if it were poſſible) as out of the mouth of Ieſus Chriſt or of his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Other doctrines laſtly are againſt the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that not onely of truth but of health al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Such are all thoſe which draw from Ieſus Chriſt and that honour which is due vnto him as the Sauiour of his people. Such is the Papall Monarchy which blemiſhes Chriſts kingdome; traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as the obiect of faith which blemiſheth Chriſts propheſie; merits, adoration of the croſſe and Images, ſacrifice of the Maſſe, Inuocation of the Saints and Angels, and all other idolatrizing points of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which blemiſh Chriſts Prieſthood, beſides other faults. To take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in and to be giuen ouer obſtinately to theſe things cannot ſtand with ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, touching times they alſo muſt haue a double conſideration. Firſt, the times before the<note place="margin">Times.</note> reſtoring of the Goſpel, when <hi>the holy citie</hi> was trod vnder foote, and the ſtate of the Church<note place="margin">Apoc. 11.</note> was deſpicable in the eyes of the world: then as God gaue his people leſſe, ſo he required leſſe at their hands. Secondly, the times after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the Goſpel. Firſt, the beaſt appeared,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15653:17"/> that curſed <hi>Antichrist,</hi> in his <hi>Pontificalibus;</hi> then<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> the Lambe ſtood vp vpon Mount <hi>Syon,</hi> with his ſealed ones; then the euerlaſting <hi>Goſpel</hi> was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched;<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.</note> and next, when the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is once reſtored,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>woe</hi> to them that take delight in the <hi>Whore,</hi> for <hi>they ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Angels, and before the Lambe, and the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſmoake of their torment ſhall aſcend euermore, and they ſhall haue no reſt, day nor night, which worſhip the Beaſt and his Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue now ſeene the danger of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and how hard a matter it is to bring them that follow it, into Chriſts Fould: How many win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and turnings, and how many diſtinctions to and fro muſt be vſed to bring them but into the iudgement of Charitie, concerning Gods looking vpon them for good.</p>
            <p>What therefore ſhall I now ſay? Let me firſt lend a word to all in generall; and next, to my brethren of the Miniſterie in particular. To all (I ſay) ſuffer the word of exhortation, both concerning our ſelues, and others: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our ſelues; ſeeing the followers of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall be damned, let not our ſoules en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into their ſecrets. As the wicked man ſhall not meddle with the Chriſtians ioy, ſo let not the good man meddle with the <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> woe.</p>
            <p>I know (my brethren) that this Conceit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in theſe generall tearmes, <hi>That a Papiſt ſo liuing and ſo dying may be ſaued,</hi> hath filled our hearts with worlds of indifferencie: So that as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15653:18"/> the <hi>Arminians</hi> haue their middle knowledge (as<note place="margin">Scientia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia. Lect. Prid. pag. 23. 24. &amp;c.</note> if there could be any cut betwixt a thing and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, a being and no being) ſo haue we had our indifferent conceits either of Proteſtancy or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery as the world ſhall ſerue and the winde ſhall turne. Hath their beene ſo much ſtriuing vnto blood in vaine? Haue ſo many martyrs loſt the crownes of their martyrdomes when they haue layed downe their liues at the feete of the Pope and his image rather then to yeeld vnto the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane abominations? Haue ſo many glorious <hi>Dauids</hi> fought the battailes of God againſt that vncircumciſed Philiſtime in vaine? Haue ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Iohns</hi> and bleſſed preachers of the Goſpel ſpent their time and ſtrength in eating of the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle booke and venting it againe to be as vials vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon<note place="margin">Apoc. 10.</note> the throne of the beaſt in vaine? No No: godly witneſſes haue not writ in vaine; victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Kings haue not fought in vaine; Conſtant martyrs haue not dyed in vaine. They haue all ſtriued as for life and death, ſaluation and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Though ſaluation may be found in the Church (as I haue ſaid) yet how hardly? If it be an hard matter to finde it any where, as, in truth it is; becauſe the law is againſt it which, were it not for the Mercy ſeate <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> would riſe out of the Arke and accuſe vs: and becauſe the creatures are againſt it which are abuſed by vs and doe call for vengeance: and becauſe euen we our ſelues are againſt it in our proneneſſe vnto ſin and delight in it) then how hard and hard againe is it to find it in the ſtye of the beaſt and amongſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15653:18"/> the followers of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> where there are ſo many killing poyſons againſt it! As therefore the Pſalmiſt ſung, <hi>Wee is mee that I remaine in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 120. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Meſhech and dwell in the Tents of Kedar:</hi> ſo may ſuch as lodge with the beaſt iuſtly ſay with griefe of heart. But as for vs that liue out of the ſmoake of the pit in the ſhining rayes of the Goſpel, let vs at the <hi>Glaſsie ſea ſing the ſong</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and of the Lambe prayſing</hi> Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as the Lord God Almightie, and his goodnes <hi>as the King of Saints,</hi> who hath deliuered vs from the yron furnace, and begun to take vengeance of that man of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, concerning others, let vs make the ſame vſe which <hi>Paul</hi> makes in this place, that is, thanke God, when we can prooue <hi>by ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>of ſpirit and faith of truth, whereunto men are called by the Goſpel to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that they are the elect of God, &amp; ſo are not in this periſhing eſtate by the works of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> We are in a naturall bond as digged out of the ſame pit by deſcending from <hi>Adam:</hi> we are in a ciuill bond, as beeing members of the ſame Church and Common-wealth: and we are of the ſame gracious bond as being members of the ſame body whereof <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> is the head. All theſe ought to mooue vs to thanke our God when we ſee men flocke from <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to the aſſemblies of the Saints, as doues to their win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes: and to exhort them to ſtand faſt in that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> courſe which they haue vndertaken by imbracing the doctrines of the Goſpel deliuered<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 15.</note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15653:19"/> vnto vs, by what meanes ſoeuer: and alſo by praying that they may be confirmed by beeing<note place="margin">Ver. 19, 17.</note> comforted in the way of grace, that all Gods people with ioyfull hearts may ſay <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Laſtly, I came to you (my Fellow-Labourers in the word of the Lord), ſeeing the danger of Popery is ſo great, and it is ſo hard a matter to bring them that delight in it into Gods fould, let vs obſerue the exhortation of bleſſed <hi>Peter,</hi> feed<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 2, 3, 4.</note> the flocke of God which dependeth vpon you, caring for it not by conſtraint but willingly; not for filthy Lucre but of a ready minde: not as though you were Lords ouer Gods Heritage, but that ye may be examples of the flock. If I ſhould doe nothing but repeate theſe wordes it were plentifully ſufficient. But oh how hardly are we drawne vnto our duties! Shall I not therefore preſſe it in particulars? Firſt then, as pittying the miſerie of <hi>Antichriſtrans,</hi> let vs feed the flock of God by the word of God. Euery thing is beſt fedde with that meate which is beſt ſutable with the nature of it, and ſo is Gods flock. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the feare of God giue them the word of God. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſhed his blood for them: is it not therefore pitty that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould defile or deſtroy them. Therefore heare the word of the Lord yee Prieſts after Gods owne heart: Preach, Catechize, and liue againſt the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, feed by preaching, that is, by ſpeaking vnto men to edification, exhortation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 3.</note> wherein as a brother to brethren let mee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15653:19"/> giue my aduice as one that hath obtained mercy. Let vs labour to ſpeake the word of God in the ſpirit of power and of a ſound mind: wee may<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 7.</note> finde by wofull and daily experience how hard a matter it is to make poor people to vnderſtand the word of God. As therefore <hi>Mannah</hi> muſt deſcend from the clouds that the people may eat of it: ſo muſt wee lay aſide all cloudy ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deſcend to vulgar apprehenſion, that the people to whom we intend good may take what is their owne and goe their way. Let vs be as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid as wee can; as the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>take heed to</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 13. 16. <hi>Prach. pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a by S. Hier.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>reading and to doctrine:</hi> but as in the building of the temple (as it is wel obſerued) there was hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the mountaines, but when it was ſet vp, not an Ax, or Sawe, or Hammer in Ieruſalem (becauſe it was to bee a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipe of the kingdome of peace): ſo though we vſe all ſortes of wrighting and wrighters in our priuate ſtudies, yet let vs not muſter and obtrude them in troopes for oſtentation in the pulpit, leaſt as <hi>Aſahels</hi> dead<note place="margin">2. Sam. 2. 23.</note> body it make the people ſtand ſtill, and cauſe them to ſay as <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> of the death of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaw a tumult but I knew not what.</hi> It is a true ſpeach of a reuerend Diuine, that learning neuer ſpoiles a good ſermon: but when it is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated either with affected eloquence, and vnuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all words, or in ſuch an abſtruſe manner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if wee meant to work admiration &amp; aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment rather then edification, wee may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps get the garlands of prayſe and goodwill rom them that liue more in the eare than in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15653:20"/> hearte, but wee ſhall neuer procure the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2. 19.</note> of ſoules, which is the crowne and ſeale of our Apoſtleſhip or miniſtery.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To ſtirre vs vp therefore to preach and thus<note place="margin">Motiues.</note> to preach think with mee (as I often haue done) of theſe foure motiues. Firſt, that our people as wee alſo breake Gods commaundements euery day both in thought, word, and deed; as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry child can ſay. They breake them all in <hi>Adam</hi> by communion, who in that one ſinne violated the whole law of nature. Yea ſince they were cut off from the old <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; graffed into <hi>Chriſt</hi> by faith they breake them by diſpoſition, and<note place="margin">Ro. 5. 12.</note> if they doe not fall into the outward acte, noe thankes to themſelues, who are as prone vnto it as a chained fox to kill yong chickens, but vnto our God who doth either reſtraine and bridle vs, or renew and ſanctifie vs to better imployments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let vs conſider that our people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thus in ſinne and errour are like vnto mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. For all the world cannot perſwade them otherwiſe till God perſwade <hi>Iaphet:</hi> yea they<note place="margin">Gen. 9. 27.</note> will ſometimes runne vpon death it ſelfe in the<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 3.</note> maintenance of their fooleries: yea and further they like madmen will raiſe great ſtirres vpon ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous matters. For as the Robe of <hi>Caeſar</hi> is ſayd more to trouble <hi>Rome</hi> than his death, and an apple to ſet all <hi>Greece</hi> on fire: ſo the Church in <hi>Chriſts</hi> time was troubled about faſting; in<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 15.</note> the Apoſtles time about ſtranguled and bloud; in the next times about the celebration of Eaſter betweene the Eaſt and Weſt Churches, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15653:20"/> that about the rites of Baptiſme, to wit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heretickes could truely baptiſe: and truely<note place="margin">Euſeb lib. 5. cap. 25. &amp; lib. 6, cap. 3.</note> theſe trifles haue benne the fuel of contention from time to time, &amp; that not only in the church but alſo among the people, as if madnes and not matter did ſway on all ſides to the diſturbing of the common peace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let vs conſider that when our people are come to knowledge they know a great deale more then they can make vſe of for their good.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4. 8.</note> As a couetous man hath no power to take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his eſtate: or as children, fooles, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent perſons may haue great honours and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes, but know not how to vſe them: ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily where the diligent hand is to diſperſe the good word of God there may be, and is a rich treaſure of precious knowledge in many of our people who know onely to know without further profit. For there is great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt knowledge for vnderſtanding, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for practiſe; as we ſee in thoſe that knew the <hi>way of the Lord and iudgement of their God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 5.</note> 
               <hi>yet they altogether brake the yoke and burſt the bonds:</hi> And againe, in thoſe who <hi>ſaid they were</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 8. 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>wiſe, and that the Law of the Lord was with them, yet they reiected the word of the Lord in power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, let vs conſider that in regard of theſe and other things our worke is neuer at an end, yea many times, yea moſt times we find it worſe then we left it. For though euery man in his trade of life doth ordinarily finde things in his buſineſſe as he left them, yet it is otherwiſe with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15653:21"/> vs: and as an huſwife findeth in her window a Copweb the next day though ſhee hath there ſwept downe one the day before, euen ſo doe we the webbes of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Now then can we conſider the fearefull brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Gods commandements, and that with ſpirituall phrenzy and madneſſe, can wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that when (thorough the aſſiſtance of God) we haue wrought them to knowledge it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite worke to bring them to practiſe: or can we thinke that our worke as the worke of a neate huſwife in an earthen roome is neuer at an end, and yet can we be idle and not feede the flocke of God by preaching? If they miſcarry tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our default, it addes to our guilt, yea a guilt guided with blood, in which reſpect <hi>Hoſea</hi> called wicked Prieſts murtherers in the way; and<note place="margin">Hoſh. 6. 9.</note> from which <hi>Paul</hi> with good conſcience cleeres himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>I take you to record this day that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20, 26.</note> 
               <hi>I am pure from the blood of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, feede by Catechiſing, that is, by contracting religion into a ſumme as <hi>Chriſt did</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 22. 37. Ioh. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>the Law and the Goſpel,</hi> that there may be a cleare and briefe ſpeaking vnto men to inſtruction. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law, <hi>Adam</hi> catechiſed <hi>Abel;</hi> which I<note place="margin">Luke 1. 4.</note> gather thus. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>by faith Abel offered vp a better ſacrifice then Kain.</hi> Now faith muſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 4.</note> the perſon which it cannot doe except there be holineſſe; and it muſt warrant the action which it cannot doe without the word: yet then there was no written word but that which was deliuered from man to man by way of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15653:21"/> and inſtruction. After the Floud, <hi>Abraham</hi> catechiſed his Family: of whom, if you aske me<note place="margin">Gen. 18. 19.</note> whether he taught them? I anſwere, Yes; from the teſtimonie of God himſelfe. If you aske me what he taught them? I anſwere, That we know that he had a perfect Body of Catechiſme giuen<note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1, 2.</note> him by God, when he ſaith, <hi>I am God all ſufficient, walke before me, and be thou vpright.</hi> For whereas the ſumme of Catechiſme doth conſiſt in faith, and obedience; <hi>I am God all-ſufficient,</hi> doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all the Doctrine of Faith; it implying his ſufficiencie, to create, to redeeme, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: <hi>Walke before me, and be thou vpright,</hi> doth comprehend the ſecond, both in reſpect of the matter, and of the manner of performance. If laſtly you will aske me, with what fruit and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe hee catechiſed? I anſwere, his ſonne went<note place="margin">Gen. 24. 63.</note> out to pray; and he had a praying ſeruant, and a<note place="margin">Ver. 12. Ver. 26. Ver. 33.</note> ſeruant that gaue thankes to God, and would not eate his meate, before hee had done his maſters buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>In the time of the Law, God commanded Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing,<note place="margin">Deut. 6. 7.</note> or whetting the Law vpon them, that it may pierce the hearts of their children to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and affect it, as the word in the originall ſignifieth. And if we will beleeue the Rabbines, there were not in Ieruſalem, from <hi>Antiochus</hi> to Chriſt, vnder foure hundred houſes for Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. In which Exerciſe they are ſaid to obſerue<note place="margin">Wei. Chriſt. Syn.</note> this order, according to the capacitie and age of them whom they did inſtruct: At fiue yeeres old they were Sonnes of the Law, to reade it:<note place="margin">Filii Legis.</note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15653:22"/> At thirteene they were called the Sonnes of the Precept, to vnderſtand the Law. Then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued<note place="margin">Filii Praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> the Paſſeouer as a Sacrament (for euen children did eate it, as a remembrance of their deliuerance out of Aegypt) and then alſo they were purified. At fifteene yeeres old they went to deeper points of the Law, and Talmudicall<note place="margin">Talmudiſtae.</note> doubts. Seeing then that it was vſed both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Floud, and after it; in the time of the Law, and after; let vs with an heauenly deſire to propagate the Truth, rowſe vp our ſpirits to doe ſo likewiſe.</p>
            <p>I reade of a certaine Heretike, who in Winter<note place="margin">Gowl. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. teſt.</note> ſeaſon did ſwimme through a certaine Riuer, to ſome to whom hee might deriue his falſehood: and ſhall wee be cold and ſluggiſh, and ſuffer a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle water to quench our loue to communicate the Truth? Oh that it might be the happineſſe of this time, that as our late renowned Soueraigne did limit after-noone Exerciſes vpon the Lords day to Catechiſing vpon the grounds of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo all Miniſters might be held vnto it, eyther by themſelues, or others! Why ſhould the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple periſh for want of knowledge, and be left ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch a temper, that they are fit matter for euery Prieſt, Ieſuit, or Sectarie to worke vpon? As therefore the woman ſaid to <hi>Dauid, Helpe O King;</hi> ſo ſay I, Helpe by our dread Soueraigne you that are to be conuocated to that end.</p>
            <p>Conſider with your ſelues what <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> ſaith, to wit, That by vertue of Catechizing there was neuer a King but receiued alteration in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15653:22"/> his Heatheniſh Religion within fourty yeares after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Therefore <hi>Iulian</hi> when hee meant<note place="margin">Acta Syn. Seſſ. 1. 5. pag. 29.</note> to ſuppreſſe religion inuented not new torments but put downe Schooles and Catechizings. The Papiſts haue confeſſed that all the grounde wee haue gotten of them is by catechiſme: and the the little grounde they haue gotten of vs is by a more diligent requiring and practiſing of it. Therefore the iudgment of the Churches in the Synode of <hi>Dort,</hi> touching this, is worthy to be written in our hearts eſpecially of our owne, that wee may no longer bee bunglers but as <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builders</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 10.</note> wee may lay the foundation, yea ſuch an one as vpon which <hi>Antichriſt</hi> may neuer bee<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 3. Gal. 2. 14.</note> ſuffered to build to the damnation of our people.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let vs feede by example: that ye may be examples of your flocke, ſaith <hi>Peter.</hi> Reaſons may perſwade but examples will draw more forecibly.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore ſet copies to our people of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and holineſſe. Firſt, let vs bee humble, not domineering ouer Gods heritage; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing with meekeneſſe the contrary-minded, and carrying our ſelues to <hi>Chriſts</hi> lambs in loue: that as <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Proctors haue humilitie in ſhew, ſo we may haue it in truth. It is well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued that the pride of the Iewiſh doctors came<note place="margin">Chriſt, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag.</note> in with the ruine of the Iewiſh Church: For, when reuelations ceaſed they vſurped ſtate and titles; one was called the light of the world, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother our holy Doctor, a third the illuſtrious, a fourth the rock of help; and they called and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15653:23"/> others but the <hi>people of the earth,</hi> and <hi>the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Populus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae. Rom. 2. 19. Crak. defenſ. contra Spal. pag. 89, 90.</note> 
               <hi>blind:</hi> ſo (diuiding the times of the Church into 3. periods; the firſt which went before <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> wherein there was nothing decreed or receiued as a doctrine of faith which is not ours; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond wherein by degrees <hi>Antichriſt</hi> came vnto his highth, and in which ſome pleaded for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and more for that man of ſinne; the third where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Antichrist</hi> beganne to decline) in the ſecond darke and leaden times the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole Hierarchy of it did ſwell with titles, which was accompanied with the ruine of mens ſoules. Let vs take heede in time. Pride we ſee hath bin a miſerable Symptome twice.</p>
            <p>Oh thou chiefe Shepherd of our ſoules driue it and keep it from vs, and work our hearts highly to eſteeme rather the flouriſhing of the Church by ſolid and powerfull preaching and catechiſing euen amongſt the pooreſt of Gods people.</p>
            <p>Let our ſecond coppy be <hi>holineſſe to the Lord</hi> vnto our people. If holineſſe to the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Gods houſe for euer, why not his neereſt ſeruants. As therefore the Iewes in the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their paſſeouer, did for foure houres<note place="margin">Godw. Moſes and Aaron, lib, 3. cap. 4. pag. 135. Chriſt. Syn.</note> ſearch out all leuen out of their houſes; and then for two houres caſt it out of their houſes; and laſtly, curſe all the leuen which they had not ſeene and could not finde: ſo let all the Prieſts of the Lords houſe be carefull to ſearch, to purge, and to execrate all the leuen of wilfull and raigning ſinne, and to oppoſe and mortifie the leaſt ſins, that we may be Prieſts after Gods owne
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15653:23"/> heart as <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeaketh. Let Popiſh Prieſts bee eminent for a Player-like grauitie and holineſſe ſo long as they are acting their maſſing part; but let vs be ſtarres in Gods right hand hauing an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward principle of the light of holines in vs from Chriſt, and ſhining forth holily vnto others, not onely in the pulpit and prayer, but in our whole courſe. What would we anſwere to ſuch Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians as ſhould ſay to <hi>Archippus, Thou that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 17.</note> 
               <hi>another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelfe? thou that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 21, 22</note> 
               <hi>preacheſt a man ſhould ſteale; doeſt thou ſteale? thou that ſayest a man ſhould not commit adultery doeſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> 
               <hi>thou commit adultery? thou that abhorreſt idols committeſt thou ſacriledge? thou that glorieſt in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Law, thorough the breaking of the Law diſhonoureſt thou God? For the name of God is blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Gentiles thorough you.</hi> Let vs tell our conſciences plainly: haue we another way to heauen then we teach our neighbours? Take heede; I ſay, take heede: amongſt all that were acceſſary to Chriſts death, the blacke gowne, I meane <hi>Iudas,</hi> was puniſhed firſt. Therefore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour againſt vnholineſſe, pray againſt it, and faſt againſt it. And oh that it might be the glory of the Church of theſe times to procure publike fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings and prayings as other Churches haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all our ſinnes? What though it be a time of reioycing in regard of our bleſſed King and gouernment. Yet anoynting the face doth not miſ-become a faſt, nor I thinke publike thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing a day of humbling. Phyſitians haue their preſeruatiues to preuent diſeaſes as well as their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15653:24"/> cures when they are come. Seeing then it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but pitty vs to ſee Syon in ſome places in the duſt; to ſee the holy Temple defiled, Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<note place="margin">Pſal. 79. 1.</note> to laugh when the blood of his Saints is<note place="margin">Pſ. 80. 5, 6.</note> ſhed like water, and they remaine are fed with the bread of teares, and haue giuen them to drinke in great meaſure: to ſee <hi>Antichriſt</hi> roare (in the Idol Maſſe) in the midſt of their congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and to ſet vp the ſignes and marks of the beaſt: And laſtly, to ſee the plague whereby God doth moſt immediatly triumph in iuſtice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his enemies, to begin to ſet footing againe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs: ſeeing, I ſay, wee ſee theſe things whoſe heart doth not hunger to make the body more hungry, and that not onely priuately but publikely: eſpecially conſidering that our ſins, euen all our ſins as well of the Church as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth doth call for theſe or greater miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries vpon vs.</p>
            <p>I will ſay but one thing more to my ſelfe and to you (my brethren like me by office) to perſwade to a greater degree of holineſſe, and then I end. Conſider that the perſon doth much commende and gaine much vpon the affections of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. <hi>Antichriſt</hi> commendes it as a principall<note place="margin">Champ. of the calling of BB. and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors.</note> principle, <hi>that firſt we must looke to the perſon tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, before we looke to the thing taught,</hi> that ſo they may bring in a ſeeming formalitie to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face true doctrine. And therefore as when <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhah</hi> accuſed the Iſraelites of Idolatry, they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him bald-pate (implying belike that he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iewiſh formalitie according to the Law,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15653:24"/> becauſe he had that blemiſh: ſo when we charge the Papiſts with ſinning againſt the word of God, they ſay that we fayle in hiſtories and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes in our entrance. But truly this is a ſilly ground thus to imbrace perſons before doctrins.</p>
            <p>For firſt Chriſt hath taught vs that what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo euer they are if they build vp the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt they muſt goe on. For when <hi>Iohn</hi> complained to him, ſaying, Maſter, we ſaw<note place="margin">Mar. 9. 38, 39, 40.</note> one caſting out diuels in thy name which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not vs: Ieſus ſaid, forbid him not, for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not againſt vs is on our part.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the New Teſtament none but the enemies of the Goſpel looke more to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then to the Doctrine: For the Prieſts and Elders ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>By what authoritie doeſt thou theſe things;</hi> and the Synod at Ieruſalem aske <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Iohn, By what power and in what name haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 21. 23.</note> 
               <hi>yee done this:</hi> but of the true worſhippers of God we heare no ſuch thing. Which I ſpeake not, as if<note place="margin">Act. 4. 7.</note> ordinarily wee ought not to aske after mens au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie (for this were the next way to leape from the Shop-board into the Pulpit, with Browniſts and other Sectaries) but to ſhew that Doctrine muſt be preferred before Perſons.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Eunuch and <hi>Lydia</hi> did not ill in hearing <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> without enquiring after their Perſons. They knew, that Chriſtians ſhould not giue an account at the day of Iudgement of the Perſons, they haue heard but of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or diſobedience to their wholeſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: yea, they knew that it was better to be led
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15653:25"/> to Heauen by a man of no Pompe, then to Hell by a Pope, vnder pretence of infallibilitie.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, moſt glorious Perſons may be full of deceit; they that come in <hi>Sheepes cloathing,</hi> may be inwardly <hi>rauening Wolues:</hi> yea, <hi>Watchmen</hi> may<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> be <hi>blinde</hi> and <hi>dumbe Dogges,</hi> that cannot barke,<note place="margin">Eſ. 56. 10, 11.</note> and <hi>greedie Dogges,</hi> that can neuer haue enough. From the Prophets euen to the Prieſts they may<note place="margin">Ier. 6. 13.</note> all deale falſely; yea, and there may be a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie of her Prophets (as in the Councell of<note place="margin">Ezek. 22. 25. Act. 20. 30.</note> Trent) in the midſt of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee, that it is a ſilly ſleight, when Rome would haue vs chiefely looke to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon teaching, before the thing taught; yet thus farre it holds, that the Perſon doth much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Worke: For the Apoſtle ſayd not in vaine, <hi>Continue in the things which thou haſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 14.</note> 
               <hi>knowing of (whom) thou haſt learned them,</hi> that is, God, yea, and (it may be) me, Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, who haue beene in thy Soule by the ſpirit of Power, which hath effectually concurred with my ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore, that our Perſons may be ſuch, that we may ſweetly ſettle our Workes vpon the hearts of thoſe that heare it, that when the chiefe Shepheard ſhall appeare, wee may receiue an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Crowne of Glory.</hi> I will end with <hi>Paul: I charge thee before God and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels, that thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5. 21.</note> 
               <hi>obſerue theſe things, without prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one to another, and doe nothing partially.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15653:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
